# Maxwell Freeman

#### PHYSICS PH.D. STUDENT

## Summary $_{-}$

Full-time research intern, who will be starting my PhD in Physics in fall of 2023 at Caltech. Currently splitting my time between a scanning probe microscopy lab and a neutral-atom quantum computing lab. Interested in using scanning probe microscopy and spectroscopy techniques to research solid-state quantum information science.

#### Education

#### California Institute of Technology

Pasadena, CA

PhD in Physics

Sept 2023

### **University of Wisconsin - Madison**

Madison, WI

BS in Physics, Astronomy, and Philosophy, with a minor in Mathematics

Sept 2018 - May 2022

- GPA: 3.98/4 via 147 credits
- Graduated with Distinction

# Research Experience

Victor Brar's SPM Lab Madison, WI

Research Assistant

April 2021 - current

- Designed/simulated a novel quasi-zero stiffness vibrational damping system in order to isolate a scanning tunneling microscope from dilution refrigerator pump noise, facilitating low-temperature, cryogen-free scanning probe microscopy
- Developed a haptic pen controller for a scanning tunneling/atomic force microscope, such that the sub-nanometer features of an atomic surface could be intuitively felt/manipulated by the user. Programmed an open-source LabVIEW library in C/C++, which interfaced the haptic device with the microscope. Supervised two high school students for the duration of the Haptic-SPM project, delegating them tasks and teaching them the necessary skills to become valuable project contributors. (publication pending)

#### Mark Saffman's Neutral Atom Quantum Computing Lab

Madison, WI

Research Assistant

Sep 2022 - current

- Assisted in running experiments in an effort to create a hybrid superconductor-atom-photon quantum interface. Used CAD to model a complete redesign of the experimental setup, using principles of UHV and cryogenic design. Also ran numerical simulations to optimize the thermodynamic properties the system.
- Gained experience working with free space optics through designing a microscopic imaging system, also employed the use of PCB/analog circuit design for various applications.

## Publications & Talks

- 1. Maxwell Freeman et al., Haptic Sensation-Based Scanning Probe Microscopy: Exploring Perceived Forces for Optimal Intuition-Driven Control. arXiv:2207.10197 (submitted).
- 2. Maxwell Freeman, A Fully-Passive, Quasi-Zero Stiffness Vibrational Isolator for Cryogen-Free Scanning Probe Microscopy. Bulletin of the American Physical Society (2023).

#### Skills \_\_\_\_\_

**Programming** C/C++, LabVIEW, Mathematica, MATLAB, Python.

Technical Software CAD (SolidWorks, KiCad, AutoCAD), SPICE (Multisim), Nanonis SPM Control Software Miscellaneous Circuit/PCB Design and Fabrication, Machine Shop Skills & Metals Fabrication, Free Space &

Fiber Optics, Arduino, Raspberry Pi.

1

# Teaching & Work Experience \_\_\_\_

Goff's Enterprises, Inc.

Pewaukee, WI

Metal Shop Technician

May 2020 - September 2020

 Worked in the metal shop cutting, forming, and finishing metal components. Gained proficiency using hand tools, CNC mills, and hydraulic presses.

#### **Greater University Tutoring Service (GUTS)**

Madison, WI

Physics Tutor

September 2019 - May 2020

- Involved working closely with undergraduate students each week, practicing and reviewing key concepts from Physics I and Physics II.
- Assisted with drop-in tutoring, where students could stop by and ask for additional math and physics help.

  Retlaw Industries, Inc.

  Hartland. WI

Assembly Technician

May 2019 - September 2019

• Worked with plastic injection molding machines, assembling and finishing the resultant plastic parts. Gained experience with assembly and plastic manufacturing techniques.

## Achievements \_\_\_\_\_

- 2021 **Inducted into the Phi Beta Kappa Honor Society**, UW Madison Chapter
- 2018 **3rd place**, UW La Crosse Calculus Competition

# References \_\_\_\_\_

Victor Brar

University of Wisconsin 
Madison

Principle Investigator vbrar@wisc.edu

Mark Saffman

University of Wisconsin 
Madison

Principle Investigator msaffman@wisc.edu